לילה טוב, Laila Tov, so we begin on, we'll do דף י"ד
Daf Yud Dalet tonight, but we'll start at the bottom of י"ג
עמוד ב', Yud Gimmel Amud Bet, ובפרקים, UvaPrakim, it's about eight lines
from the bottom. And this is now we had discussed before about
the issue of כוונה, Kavana, and now we're dealing with when can
you interrupt at different stages. So let's take a look. ובפרקים שואל
מפני הכבוד. Uvaprakim Shoel MiPnei HaKavod. So the first position was that
of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that said that at the breaks you
can ask somebody's well-after their well-being for honor and you can respond.
So the גמרא Gemara says משיב מחמת מאי? Meshiv Machmas Mai? Under
what conditions can you respond? אילימא מפני הכבוד, Ileima MiPnei HaKavod, if
it's out of again a situation in which it's an issue about
giving proper honor,
so התם משואל אדובי מיבעיא? Hatam MiShoel Aduvei MiBa'aya? If you can
ask, if you can initiate, then certainly it's always it should be
a lowest threshold, certainly not a higher one in order to respond
where it's more expected of you.
So why do you have to bother mentioning that you can respond
if you already said that you can initiate? אלא שואל מפני הכבוד
ומשיב שלום לכל אדם. Ella Shoel MiPnei HaKavod U'Meshiv Shalom Lechol Adam.
So maybe when רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you can respond, it
means you can respond even at a lower threshold, even if it's
not an issue of honor, even if it's a normal person. So
the גמרא Gemara says אימא סיפא, Eima Seifa, so now let's continue,
look at the end. ובאמצע שואל מפני היראה ומשיב. Ube'Emtza Shoel MiPnei
HaYirah U'Meshiv. In the middle of a chapter, of a section, you
can ask only if it's out of a sense of
fear and you can respond. So משיב מחמת מאי? Meshiv Machmas Mai?
What are we responding to, what situation? אילימא מפני היראה, Ileima MiPnei
HaYirah, again it's a situation of fear, so same issue. Why do
you have to say it? התם משואל אדובי מיבעיא? Hatam MiShoel Aduvei
MiBa'aya? If you can ask, if you can initiate an ask, how
much more so can you respond? So you wouldn't have to mention
that you can respond. אלא, Ella, it must be when he says
you can respond, it means even at a lower threshold, מפני הכבוד.
MiPnei HaKavod.
So it must be that you can respond even if it's just
out of honor. So now what we have him saying, because רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir said respond, respond and didn't clarify what, and the
only way it makes sense to bother saying it is if he's
giving a lower threshold, then that becomes exactly the position of
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So the גמרא Gemara says היינו דרבי יהודה.
Hainu DeRabbi Yehuda. Winds up being רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתנן, Detnan,
we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, רבי יהודה אומר באמצע שואל מפני
היראה ומשיב
מפני הכבוד.
Rabbi Yehuda Omer Be'Emtza Shoel MiPnei HaYirah U'Meshiv
MiPnei HaKavod. In the middle of a section, you can ask out
of fear and you can respond out of honor. So it's a
lower threshold. ובפרקים, UvaPrakim, between the sections, שואל מפני הכבוד ומשיב שלום
לכל אדם, Shoel MiPnei HaKavod U'Meshiv Shalom Lechol Adam, that you can
initiate and ask out of
honor and you can respond to everyone. So this is exactly what
we said that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was saying. So basically it
boils down to what does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir mean when he
says respond.
If he means the same
thing then it's obvious, if he means a different threshold then it
is the position of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So the גמרא Gemara
says hey people by the way we're
talking about באמצע, Be'Emtza, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is talking about בפרקים,
BaPrakim, so there's a difference.
No, no, no, they're talking about both. Take a look. They it
was an ABBA order but they're both saying, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is saying, they both agree that you can what you can be
שואל, Sho'el, that between the פרקים Prakim you can be שואל Sho'el
for כבוד Kavod and in the middle of a פרק Perek you
can be שואל Sho'el for יראה. Yirah. And then רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir was not clear under what circumstances you can respond, and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said you can respond in both cases with a
lower threshold. So take a look, it's just it's a little confusing
because the order is ABBA. But basically you're saying that if he
means a lower threshold then it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, if he
means the same threshold then it's redundant. The גמרא Gemara continues, hey
people by the way again put it on mute unless you want
to say something, we're getting feedback. The גמרא Gemara continues and says
okay,
everybody please put it on mute unless you want to say something.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. Chasuri Michasra VeHachi Katani.
So you're right, it's really missing some words and here's what it
should say. It doesn't necessarily mean it's missing words but here's the
implicit context. ובפרקים שואל מפני הכבוד ואין צריך לומר שמשיב. UvaPrakim Shoel
MiPnei HaKavod VeEin Tzarich Lomar SheMeshiv. And
when רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you respond, he doesn't mean a
lower threshold. He's saying there's no lower threshold, that between the sections
it can be out of honor, you can initiate and you can
respond, you don't have to say it, but the point is to
say that it's not a different threshold, that he's not saying רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position. ובאמצע, Ube'Emtza, in the middle, שואל מפני היראה
ואין צריך לומר שמשיב. Shoel MiPnei HaYirah VeEin Tzarich Lomar SheMeshiv. You
can ask out of fear and obviously you can respond if you
can initiate, you can respond, but again the point being that to
emphasize that the threshold isn't lower, that he's not saying רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda position. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי
מאיר Meir says. רבי יהודה אומר באמצע שואל מפני היראה ומשיב מפני
הכבוד. Rabbi Yehuda Omer Be'Emtza Shoel MiPnei HaYirah U'Meshiv MiPnei HaKavod. In
the middle you can ask out of fear but there's a lower
threshold, you can respond out of honor. ובפרקים, UvaPrakim, and between the
sections, שואל מפני הכבוד ומשיב שלום לכל אדם. Shoel MiPnei HaKavod U'Meshiv
Shalom Lechol Adam. That you can ask out of honor and respond
to everyone. But what it's saying is you're right, it is redundant
to say it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir does
not have a different threshold, but the point of saying it is
the setup for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
can say you're not distinguishing between initiating and responding, I am going
to distinguish and I'm going to make a lower threshold for responding.
Okay. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, it taught explicitly that way
in a ברייתא, braita, second line of יג עמוד א. yud gimmel
amud aleph. הקורא את שמע ופגע בו רבו או גדול הימנו, Ha-kore
et shema u-paga bo rabbo o gadol heimenu, so
if you're reading שמע shema and your teacher or your רב Rav
encounters you or a person of greater honor, and therefore there's a...
of the norms of societal expectations, there's a requirement to ask after
their well-being, it's an issue of כבוד. kavod. So therefore in those
cases, what do you do? שואל מפני הכבוד, shoel mipnei ha-kavod, you
can ask, you can initiate because of honor, ואין צריך לומר שהוא
משיב, ve-ein tzarich lomar she-hu meshiv, and of course you can respond.
Same threshold, but if you can ask you can respond. ובאמצע u-ve-emtza
and if you're in the middle of a section, שואל מפני היראה,
shoel mipnei ha-yirah, you can even initiate if it's out of awe
then you can even in the middle of a section you can
initiate, ואין צריך לומר שהוא משיב ve-ein tzarich lomar she-hu meshiv and
there's no different threshold for initiating than responding. Also you can respond
only out of awe, no lower threshold. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi
Meir, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi
Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says I agree to the initiating
but I think there's a lower threshold for responding. באמצע שואל מפני
היראה ומשיב מפני הכבוד, be-emtza shoel mipnei ha-yirah u-meshiv mipnei ha-kavod, in
the middle you're right, you can only initiate out of awe but
you can respond even out of honor. ובפרקים u-va-perakim and between the
sections, שואל מפני הכבוד, shoel mipnei ha-kavod, I
again agree with you that you can initiate out of honor, ומשיב
שלום לכל אדם u-meshiv shalom le-chol adam to respond it's a lower
threshold. So basically yes, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir did not have to
say משיב, meshiv, it's redundant, but he just said it in order
to make it clear that he wasn't distinguishing to be a lead
up to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who was distinguishing. Okay, and now
the גמרא Gemara continues. And before the גמרא Gemara continues, because the
גמרא's Gemara now going to ask what is the הלכה halacha about
this when it's not שמע, shema, when it's something else. But before
we get to that I want to take a moment to look
at תוספות, Tosafot, because תוספות Tosafot says within the context of שמע,
shema, how does this issue of responding to people relate to the
issue of responding to דאבנינג? davening? So if you take a look
on יג עמוד ב yud gimmel amud bet at the תוספות Tosafot
שואל מפני היראה, shoel mipnei ha-yirah,
תוספות Tosafot says like this: רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה הלכה כרבי יהודה,
Rabbi Meir ve-Rabbi Yehuda halacha ke-Rabbi Yehuda, so we're going to rule
like we in general rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and I
think the גמרא Gemara says it explicitly later. So therefore you can
respond even in the middle of a section, you can respond out
of honor. And תוספות Tosafot makes a pretty logical analogy. He says
like this: דאמר אפילו באמצע משיב מפני הכבוד, d'amar afilu be-emtza meshiv
mipnei ha-kavod,
so therefore if you're in the middle of saying קריאת שמע, kriat
shema, you're in the middle of a
section, so they're saying קדיש וקדושה, kaddish u-kedusha, there's an expectation for
you to respond, certainly giving honor to God's name is equivalent to
giving honor to a person. So if you can respond to a
person, you can respond to קדיש וקדושה. kaddish u-kedusha. דאין לך מפני
הכבוד גדול מזה. de-ein le-cha mipnei ha-kavod gadol mi-zeh. אבל באמצע שמונה
עשרה אסור. aval be-emtza shmoneh esrei assur.
That's only in the middle of שמע, shema, שמונה עשרה shmoneh esrei
obviously has a different status. Okay, so this becomes an interesting discussion,
not when can you respond to people, mostly that's not an issue
for us, but what is much more of an abiding issue is
you're דאבנינג davening and you're in a different place than everybody else,
can you respond to קדיש וקדושה kaddish u-kedusha and so on. תוספות
Tosafot wants to say that those types of things are equivalent to
the הלכה halacha of מפני הכבוד. mipnei ha-kavod. Okay, there's obviously more
to say about that but just to see the comparison that תוספות
Tosafot makes. Now to return to the גמרא, Gemara, יג עמוד א,
yud gimmel amud aleph,
about eight lines down. So now that we're done with שמע shema
and what you can interrupt, we're going to talk about things that
are other types of things whether they can be interrupted or not.
הגמרא ha-Gemara says like this: בעי מיניה האי תנא דבי רבי חייא
מרבי חייא. be'ei minei hai tanna d'vei Rabbi Chiyya me-Rabbi Chiyya.
So a certain תנא tanna of the school of רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiyya asked רבי חייא: Rabbi Chiyya: בהלל ובמגילה מהו? be-Hallel u-ve-Megilla mahu?
What's the story about interrupting הלל Hallel and מגילה? Megilla? Also because
of כבוד kavod or יראה? yirah? How does that compare to the
שמע shema question? מהו שיפסיק? mahu she-yafsik? Can you interrupt? מי אמרינן
קל וחומר? mi amrinan kal va-chomer? It's a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer.
קריאת שמע דאורייתא, kriat shema de-oraita, קריאת שמע kriat shema is biblical,
פוסק, posek, you can interrupt. הלל דרבנן מיבעיא? Hallel de-rabbanan mibaya? הלל
Hallel and מגילה Megilla which are only rabbinic, it's less weighty, how
much more so should you be able to interrupt based on similar
thresholds? או דלמא, o dilma, or do we say, פרסומי ניסא עדיף?
pirsumei nisa adif? No, הלל Hallel and מגילה Megilla have a unique
character of sort of publicizing the miracle and
maybe therefore it's again not clear, are you talking about in private
or in public? Certainly if it's in public you don't want to
be interrupting because it's a public experience, but maybe even in private,
the quality of פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa which is a less common
opportunity to do those types of things and maybe that has a
certain weight that doesn't allow that the interruption would somehow undermine that
and maybe it should be different. So what's the story? Do we
have a higher threshold for those? אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiyya said back, פוסק ואין בכך כלום. posek ve-ein be-kach
klum. You can interrupt, don't have to worry about it at all.
Now it's not clear from that answer whether he says it's just
like שמע shema or maybe it's even more lenient than שמע. shema.
אין בכך כלום ein be-kach klum sounds like don't worry about it
at all, maybe it's even easier than שמע. shema. Not clear, but
Now it's not clear from that answer whether he says it's, whether
he says it's just like שמע, Shema, or maybe it's even more
lenient than שמע. Shema. אין בכך כלום ein bekach klum sounds like
don't worry about it at all, maybe it's even easier than שמע.
Shema. Not clear, but certainly it's not more stringent. And now the
גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, ימים שיחיד גומר בהן את
ההלל, yamim sheyachid gomer bahen et haHallel, the days that an individual
says הלל, Hallel,
which means days we say a full הלל. Hallel. I'll talk about
that phrase in a minute. But the days that we say a
full הלל, Hallel, בין פרק לפרק פוסק, באמצע הפרק אינו פוסק. bein
perek leperek posek, be'emtza haperek eino posek.
So between, between one chapter and the next you can interrupt like
שמע, Shema, between sections, but not in the middle of a section.
ימים שאין היחיד גומר בהן את ההלל, yamim she'ein hayachid gomer bahen
et haHallel, and the days, however, that you're not saying a full
הלל, Hallel, you're only saying a half הלל, Hallel, אפילו באמצע הפרק
פוסק, afilu be'emtza haperek posek, you can even interrupt in the middle
of a chapter because there it is not really like the full
weight, full status of a הלל, Hallel, it's probably, it's only a
מנהג minhag anyway, so it's even of a lighter weight. Now what's
not clear about this is when he says you can interrupt, is
he talking about מפני היראה mipnei hayirah or מפני הכבוד? mipnei hakavod?
Let's assume that he's talking about מפני הכבוד. mipnei hakavod. So therefore
it has the same הלכה halacha of שמע. Shema. If you're saying
a full הלל, Hallel, it has the same הלכה halacha of שמע.
Shema. You can interrupt מפני הכבוד mipnei hakavod in between, in between
sections, but not in the middle of a section. And when you
say a חצי הלל, chatzi Hallel, it's even more lenient. So let's
see where the גמרא Gemara continues.
איני, Eini, is this really true? והא רב בר שבא איקלע לגבי
דרבינא, Veha Rav Bar Shaba ikla legabei deRavina, רב בר שבא Rav
Bar Shaba came to רבינא, Ravina, ויומי דאין היחיד גומר בהן את
ההלל הוה, veyomei de'ein hayachid gomer bahen et haHallel hava, and
it
was a day where we were saying
a חצי הלל chatzi Hallel like ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, הוה, hava,
ולא פסק ליה, velo pasak lei,
and he didn't interrupt. So you see that you said you can,
again, this is presumably an issue of כבוד, kavod, and we just
said that full הלל Hallel is like שמע, Shema, you can do
it in between chapters, but חצי הלל chatzi Hallel is even more
lenient, even in the middle of a chapter. And he says, but
it's not true, they were doing a חצי הלל chatzi Hallel and
he didn't interrupt in the middle of a chapter. So the גמרא
Gemara says, שאני רב בר שבא דלא חשיב עליה
דרבינא. shani Rav Bar Shaba delo chashiv alei deRavina. Says, who told
you it was an issue of כבוד? kavod? רבינא Ravina did not
give so much חשיבות, chashivut, so much weight, you know, honor to
רב בר שבא. Rav Bar Shaba. He felt he was כל אדם,
kol adam, he didn't feel it was מפני הכבוד, mipnei hakavod, and
that's why he didn't interrupt. So that's a very interesting commentary about
their relationship or about how they, they value, you know, sort of
valued one another. But nevertheless, the basic upshot is, is that full
הלל Hallel is the same as שמע, Shema, and חצי הלל chatzi
Hallel is more lenient. Now I want to say something about the
phrase יחיד גומר בהן את ההלל. yachid gomer bahen et haHallel. Why
there's a huge תוספות Tosafot which finally gives us a normal sized
דף daf for once? So first point is that I'll get to
the phrase יחיד yachid in a minute, but the first question is
there's a major מחלוקת ראשונים machloket Rishonim whether you say a ברכה
bracha by חצי הלל, chatzi Hallel, since חצי הלל chatzi Hallel is
only a מנהג minhag anyway. And תוספות Tosafot is generally of the
position that you do. One of תוספות's's Tosafot arguments that you say
it is that the גמרא Gemara wouldn't have had had to need
to have had any discussion of interrupting, even at a lower threshold,
if there was no ברכה. bracha. According to תוספות, Tosafot, there's no
concern of interrupting if there's not an issue of being framed by
a ברכה bracha and somehow the interrupting is interrupting a ברכה bracha
or interrupting an act framed by a ברכה. bracha. So that's one
of his proofs that you are making a ברכה bracha by חצי
הלל. chatzi Hallel. Now I don't know that's so clear. I mean,
let's say for example, I don't
know, there's a ספק safek if I was יוצא מגילה, yotzei Megillah,
so I'm reading מגילה Megillah again. All of a sudden the laws
of interrupting don't apply just because there's no ברכה? bracha? You know,
so it's an interesting assumption that תוספות Tosafot makes, that the laws
of interrupting requires this idea of a ברכה bracha and tries to
bring a proof from that. And what's actually more interesting about that
is that leads him to a discussion of the הלל Hallel we
say on the סדר Seder night. And he says, since we break
up that הלל Hallel with the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, with the
סעודה, seudah, half before and half after, you obviously can't be saying
a ברכה bracha for that הלל. Hallel. And
because there were some opinions that you did say a ברכה bracha
for that הלל. Hallel. Okay, but even with that, that just proves
that if you can't, you certainly can't interrupt if there is a
ברכה. bracha. But it doesn't prove the opposite, that if there's no
ברכה bracha there's no issue of interruption. So it's interesting that תוספות
Tosafot sees the interrupting to be about around the issue of ברכה.
bracha. One other comment about the phrase יחיד גומר בהן את ההלל.
yachid gomer bahen et haHallel. Why does it say an individual completes
the הלל? Hallel? So basically תוספות Tosafot says the word יחיד yachid
here is really, you know, not so significant. It really no difference
between an individual and a ציבור. tzibur. But there are those that
definitely read that no, that the point is, is that on the
days of חצי הלל chatzi Hallel where we say, a יחיד yachid
isn't גומר בהן את ההלל. gomer bahen et haHallel. but maybe a
ציבור *Tzibur* is. Maybe maybe not saying a full הלל *Hallel*, but
meaning maybe the point being that there's a difference on the days
of חצי הלל *Chatzi Hallel* between the obligation of the ציבור *Tzibur*
and the obligation of the יחיד *Yachid*. And there definitely are some
that say that if you are, if you're saying a חצי הלל
*Chatzi Hallel* and you're not in שול *shul* and you're ביחידות *beyachidus*,
you don't make a ברכה bracha *bracha*. That even the מנהג *minhag*
of חצי הלל *Chatzi Hallel* is only at the ציבור *Tzibur* level
and not at the יחיד *Yachid* level. So that's just one way
of understanding what this phrase of the יחיד *Yachid*, the individual, says
a full הלל *Hallel*, that there could be a different status for
the ציבור *Tzibur*. Okay, but that is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s discussion
that in the end concludes that presumably, even though these are דרבנן
*derabbanan*, they have basically the same status as שמע Shema. *Shema*, not
a higher one, not a lower one. And now we continue. Okay,
so, and now we're going to continue, it's going to be a
bit of a digression based on this phrase of אין בכך כלום
*ein bekach klum*. So let's take a look. בעא מיניה אשיאן תנא
דבי רב Rav, אמי מרב אמי *Ba'ei minei Ashian tana devei Rav
Ami meRav Ami*. Also, once again, you have a similar type of
a framework that a תנא *tana* of Rabbi Chiyya's school asked Rabbi
Chiyya, and now a תנא *tana* of Rabbi Ami's school asked Rabbi
Ami. And here was the question: השרוי בתענית מהו שיטעום *Hasharuy betaanis
mahu sheyitam*? If somebody is accepting a תענית *taanis*, an individual private
fast day,
are you allowed to, like, taste something on your, you know, on
your tongue? You're preparing, let's say, the meal for after the fast.
Can you, like, taste, you know, the food that you're preparing? אכילה
ושתיה קבלה עליה *Achilah ushtiyah kabbilah alei*? Is it only your, and
the פסוק pasuk *posuk* says the phrase קבלה עליה *kabbilah alei*, have
you accepted upon yourself? תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* understands that this is only
about a private fast; if it was a public fast, it would,
it might have different standards. But at least for a private fast,
do we say fundamentally you're, you're saying I'm not going to eat
or drink, והא ליכא *veha leka*, and this isn't real eating, it's
just, you know, tip of my tongue, it's just tasting, it's not
real eating? או דלמא *Od dilma*, or do we say הנאה קבלה
עליה *hana'ah kabbilah alei*, that I'm not going to get any pleasure
from food? והא איכא *Veha ika*, so it's not an act of
eating, but I'm certainly ingesting, food is going in me and I'm,
I'm getting, you know, pleasure from it. So how do we understand
the nature of תענית *taanis*? So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says, אמר
amar, ליה *amar lei*, so he said back to him, Rav Ami
said back to him, טועם ואין בכך כלום *to'em ve'ein bekach klum*.
Yeah, eat, you can taste it, no problem. So again, the same
phrase, like a תנא *tana* asked and the answer was אין בכך
כלום *ein bekach klum*, you know, it's not an issue at all,
don't even worry about it at all. תניא נמי הכי מטעמת אינה
טעונה ברכה bracha, *Tanya nami hachi, mat'emes einah teunah bracha*. If somebody
just tastes, you don't, interesting, it's in the feminine, maybe imagine's a
woman preparing the meals,
does not, does not require a ברכה bracha *bracha*. And והשרוי בתענית
טועם ואין בכך כלום *vehasharuy betaanis to'em ve'ein bekach klum*. And similarly,
if somebody is in a fast day, you can taste and it's
not a problem. Taste is not the same as eating. עד כמה
*Ad kamah*? How much can you taste and it's not a problem?
ואמרי רב אמי ורב אסי טעמי עד שיעור רביעתא *Veaamri Rav Ami
veRav Assi ta'ami ad shiur revi'asa*. So Rav Ami and Rav Assi
say you can taste until the, until a רביעית *revi'is*, until like
three and a half ounces or so, it's considered just a taste.
Now if you take this גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* on face value, it's
an enormous חידוש *chiddush*, right? Because that's a lot of tasting that
you're doing. And to say that it's not a תענית *taanis* problem
or it's not a ברכה bracha, *bracha* problem is a pretty big
חידוש *chiddush*. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* qualifies immediately, if you take a
look at תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*, טועם ואין בכך כלום *to'em ve'ein bekach
klum*, he says פירוש רק שחוזר ופולט *peirush rak shechozer upolet*. You
spit it out. Okay. דלא חשיב הנאה *Delo chashiv hana'ah*. Because otherwise,
he says, why is it not eating? You're putting it in your
mouth, you're putting it on your tongue, it's a little bit at
a time, what makes it tasting and not eating? So he says
what we're really talking about is that you taste it and then
you spit it out, and therefore there was no attempt to ingest.
Obviously, something went in your body or else you wouldn't have had
any taste, but fundamentally there was no swallowing, there's no ingest, there's
just a tasting and a spitting out. So that's how תוספות *Tosafos*
explains this and why this is different. There is a fascinating debate
about these issues in the פוסקים *poskim*, like if I just put
something at the tip of my tongue, okay, is that maybe a
different act than eating? Like if I want, there's a whole question
about, you know, tasting a liver, and is it salted and is
there still a blood taste, like maybe there's even an איסור *issur*
taste and you're tasting for it. Are you allowed to do that
if it's something at the tip of your tongue, does that have
a different status? So that might have been what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* was talking about, that might be what makes טעימה *te'imah* not
אכילה *achilah*. תוספות *Tosafos* says it has to do with the aspect
of spitting it out. Okay, but quite a sort of fascinating distinction
of tasting versus eating. And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues, back
to our major theme. אמר רב כל הנותן *Amar Rav kol hanosein*,
excuse me, not exactly our major theme. כל הנותן שלום לחבירו קודם
שיתפלל כאילו עשאו במה bammeh *Kol hanosein shalom lechavero kodem sheyispalel ke'ilu
asa'o bamah*. At least we're back to תפילה tefilla, *tefillah*, but actually
this is again with a digression. Anybody who welcomes somebody, שלום עליכם
*shalom aleichem*, before, before דאווענינג *davening*, is like you made them into
an altar. Now, of course, this is related to our topic because
we've been talking about שלום *shalom*, about being שואל בשלום *sho'el beshalom*
and welcoming somebody. So if you go over to somebody and say
שלום עליכם *shalom aleichem*, how are you doing or whatever and you
haven't דאווענט *davened* yet, then you are, then you are, you know,
fundamentally addressing... you were
your wishes to this person and not to God. So therefore you've
turned him into an altar, כאילו עשהו במה, bammeh שנאמר shene'emar as
the פסוק pasuk. says: חדלו לכם מן האדם, chidlu lachem min ha-adam,
cease from people, from turning your face to people, אשר נשמה באפו
asher neshamah b'apo that has breath in its mouth in its nose,
כי במה נחשב ki bammeh nechshav because what value is he? במה
bamah, like of what value is he, הוא. hu. אל תקרי al
tikri במה of what value, אלא במה. ella bamah. You have נחשב,
nechshav, you have made him into a במה, into an altar. You
have offered up your
wishes to this person rather than to God. Now of course this
ties in a little bit to the earlier גמרא Gemara about tasting,
about eating before דאוונען davening and about casting God behind your back.
So there it was maybe about doing other things or taking care
of your own interest. Here there's even a different quality to it.
It's about giving honor to a person before honor to God, and
that has even
almost a little bit even of an עבודה זרה avodah zarah quality
to it is the subtext here of this גמרא. Gemara ושמואל אמר
u-Shmuel amar במה חשבת לזה ולא לאלוה? bammeh chishavta l'zeh v'lo l'Eloha?
And if that was not clear, שמואל Shmuel makes it clear. שמואל
Shmuel says: במה חשבת לזה ולא לאלוה? bammeh chishavta l'zeh v'lo l'Eloha?
What are you doing giving significance to this person
and not to God? So therefore you're directing
your honor to the wrong place. מתיב רב
ששת. masiv Rav Sheshet. So now on this we're going to ask,
because our משנה Mishnah deals with saying hello to people before they've
דאוונענד davened and before you've דאוונענד. davened. בפרקים שמפני
הכבוד ומשיב ומשיב,
b'prakim she-mipnei ha-kavod
u-meshiv u-meshiv, you can ask people after their well-being. So how can
you do that? You just told me it was אסור assur to
ask after somebody's well-being before you דאוונען. daven. תרגמה רב אבא במשכים
לפתחו. targemah Rav Abba b'mashkim l'pischo. That no, you're right. If you
bump into somebody you
can ask after their well-being; it would be insulting not to. When
we say this problem of like you made this person into an
altar, that's when you go out of your way and you knock
on their door, you rise up early to knock on their door
and to welcome them in the morning before דאוונען. davening. There you
really are doing a whole effort of giving honor to this person
and an initiative of going out of your way to give honor
to this person before you focus on your דאוונען. davening. That's the
problem. Not when he happens to walk in and you're in the
middle and you have to respond to his presence and to interrupt.
I should also mention by the
way that
in Roman culture there was this whole phenomenon of patronage. I forget
the details but there was this whole sort of phenomenon of patronage
and that the higher class was like a patron to the class
below them, had patrons
directly below them
and gave them connections and gave them financial assistance, and their responsibility,
it's sort of like feudalism but not as bad, their responsibility was
basically to come early in the morning to welcome the person, to
sort of be his retinue, to tend on him hand and foot
and so on. So that was like a whole nature of a
societal construct there of driving early in the morning to your patron
and showing them honor. So the גמרא, Gemara, that I think is
a little more punch to the point that the גמרא Gemara is
saying is: don't start doing all that stuff and making this guy
so חשוב chashuv before you at least have recognized God and have
דאוונענד davened first. Okay. And now the גמרא Gemara. says the following.
We'll skip the parentheses. אמר רב אידי בר אבין אמר רב יצחק
בר אשין: amar Rav Idi bar Abin amar Rav Yitzchak bar Ashyan:
אסור לו לאדם שלאסות חפציו קודם שיתפלל. assur lo l'adam she-la'asot chafatzav
kodem she-yispallel.
So that was specifically about honor to a person but now even
more broadly, similar to the גמרא Gemara also about casting God behind
your back just doing other things giving them priority, you can't take
care of your own interests before you דאוונען. daven. שנאמר: צדק לפניו
יהלך וישם לדרך פעמיו. shene'emar tzedek lefanav yehalech ve-yasem la-derech pe'amav.
Righteousness will go in front of him and it will place on
the path his feet. So first צדק לפניו יהלך. tzedek l'fanav yehalech.
First the righteousness has to precede you. I think רש"י Rashi here
explains right: תפילה שמצדיקו לבוראו, tefillah she-matzdiko l'boro,
that your prayer which basically
justifies you to your Creator, acknowledges God as the one who created
you
and gives that acknowledgment, that goes first. And then וישם פעמיו, v'yasem
pe'amav, then you can put your feet down and go on your
rest of the path for the day. ואמר רב אידי בר אבין
אמר רב יצחק בר אשין. v'amar Rav Idi bar Abin amar Rav
Yitzchak bar Ashyan. All right? I'm sorry. Is this like
the morning
דאוונען davening not the מנחה? Minchah?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. All of this is about the morning דאוונען
davening
because הגיע זמן תפילה higi'ah zman tefillah for מנחה Minchah and מעריב
Maariv is just a side issue about will you forget. But absolutely
and thank you for qualifying. All of these statements about eating and
doing other things and welcoming people, all of that is the first
דאוונען davening of the
day, and basically for the reason that your day has to start
with this acknowledgment of God and then other things can follow. But
you know, once your day started that way, then when it comes
to the second and the third דאווענען, davening, it’s no longer an
issue. You’ve already, in a way, sort of, you know, started your
day by recognizing, you know, that God has created you and what
you owe God and your relationship to God and so on. But
don’t, so it’s all very much about the first דאווענען. davening. You’re
absolutely correct. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara just concludes with this
about this point. רב אדי בר אבין Rav Addi bar Avin said
in the name of רב יצחק בר אשיאן, Rav Yitzchak bar Ashyan,
and again the same מן דאמר man de-amar here, the same, you
know, sort of line of tradition. כל המתפלל ואחר כך יוצא לדרך,
kol ha-mitpallel ve-ahar kach yotzei la-derech, if you first דאווען, daven, you
do the right thing and then you go out on your way.
You know, sometimes someone, the plane is going or whatever, you have
to leave and דאווען daven at the airport or something, sometimes you
don’t always have a choice. But if you can דאווען daven before
you go out on your way, then הקדוש ברוך הוא עושה לו
חפציו, Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu oseh lo chafatzav, then God will take care
of your needs. Right,
like the flip of אסור לאדם לעשות חפציו, asur le-adam la-asot chafatzav,
don’t you take care of your חפציו. chafatzav. You דאווען daven first
and then God will take care of your חפציו. chafatzav. God will
make sure things work out. שנאמר shene'emar: צדק לפניו יהלך וישם לדרך
פעמיו. tzedek l'fanav yehalech v'yasem l'derech pe'amav. First have the צדק, tzedek,
first come first and then go on your way. Similar point, but
here’s specifically in the context of taking a trip. Okay, now we
end it with this sort of, this strand with another sort of,
few more aggadic statements. אמר רב יונה אמר רב זירא, amar Rav
Yona amar Rav Zeira, כל הלן שבעת ימים בלא חלום, kol ha-lan
shivat yamim belo chalom, if you sleep for seven days without a
dream, נקרא רע, nikra ra, you are called evil. I don’t know
exactly what sort of the moral significance is of that, but שנאמר
ושבע ילין בל יפקד רע, shene'emar ve-sava yalin bal yipaked ra, and
you will sort of sleep sated, not be visited by evil. So
that’s שבע. sava. אל תקרי שבע אלא שבע. al tikrei sava ela
sheva. If שבע sheva ילין, yalin, if you sleep for seven days
בל יפקד bal yipaked and you’re not visited by a dream, then
רע, ra, then you’re evil. Presumably this has something to do with
the belief, you know, that the גמרא, Gemara. you know, some different
אמוראים Amoraim give different weight to the significance of dreams, but that
the dreams somehow are some messages from the spiritual world. So if
that’s what you believe, whether they’re sort of, you know, clear messages
or not, but if you believe that there’s something of that nature
and you’re not getting any messages for a whole week, then that’s
a bad sign. And then the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר ליה רב
אחא בריה דרב חייא בר אבא הכי אמר רבי חייא אמר רבי
יוחנן. amar leh Rav Acha breh de-Rav Chiya bar Abba hachi amar
Rabbi Chiya amar Rabbi Yochanan. Here’s what רב חייא בר אבא Rav
Chiya bar Abba says in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
about this פסוק. pasuk, כל המשביע עצמו מדברי תורה ולן, kol ha-masbia
atzmo mi-divrei Torah ve-lan, a more closer to the original meaning of
the
פסוק, pasuk if you satiate yourself with words of תורה Torah and
then go to sleep, like you fill up yourself with תורה Torah
before bedtime, אין מבשרים אותו בשורות רעות, ein mevasrim oto besurot ra'ot,
then you will not be visited with evil reports, with bad things.
שנאמר ושבע ילין, shene'emar ve-sava yalin, if you go to sleep sated
with תורה, Torah, בל יפקד רע, bal yipaked ra, you will not
be visited by anything evil. Okay, so. By the way, Rabbi?
Yes. I heard an explanation in the name of the אלשיך Alshich
about the dream, that basically if you go seven days without realizing
that the world is temporary, sort of like a dream, then you’re
called רשע. rasha. So for six days you can be excused because
you know you’re doing your מלאכה, melacha, but on the seventh day
which one of them has to include a שבת, Shabbat, right, where
you’re free to just, you know, pursue spiritual activities, then if you
don’t realize that, you know, there’s more to, you know, that this
world isn’t so temp isn’t, if you don’t realize the world is
temporary, then you know you’ve then you’re evil because you haven’t realized
the purpose of this world which is to grow spiritually.
Okay very nice, יישר כוח. yasher koach. Okay very nice, יישר כוח.
yasher koach. It's also not clear to me exactly why this statement
is here in the גמרא. Gemara It’s not so clear how it
has a thematic connection and it doesn’t seem like it's connected, it’s
the same מן דאמר man de-amar as before that I can see.
So, not exactly clear what the connection is. I’m sorry, what?
I thought we skipped אמר רב יונה אמר רב
זירא.
amar Rav Yona
amar Rav Zeira. I thought we skipped.
Oh, the parentheses! Oh, יישר כוח. yasher koach. So that should be
a good argument to keep the parentheses in. So thank you very
much. You’re right, the parentheses which was taken out by the מהרש"א
Maharsha was אמר רב יונה אמר רב זירא, amar Rav Yona amar
Rav Zeira, and there is therefore another statement of רב יונה אמר
רב זירא. Rav Yona amar Rav Zeira. Excellent. So we need to
put the parentheses back in. Okay, now we continue. אלו הן בין
הפרקים. eilu hein bein ha-prakim. So then it gives you, you know,
the between the sections and basically it’s where you would expect the
between the sections to be. But again, like the first ברכה beracha.
is a big ברכה, bracha it doesn’t go by paragraphs there. The
whole ברכה bracha is one section, then the next ברכה, bracha then
each פרשה parsha of שמע. Shema Then becomes the debate in the
משנה Mishnah about between the last פרשה parsha of
שמע Shema. and אמת ויציב, Emet ve-Yatziv, is that a בין הפרקים.
bein ha-prakim. So let's take a look. אמר רב אבהו אמר רבי
יוחנן, amar Rav Avahu amar Rabbi Yochanan, הלכה כרבי יהודה. halacha ke-Rabbi
Yehuda. We rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, דאמר בין אלוהיכם לאמת
ויציב לא יפסיק. de-amar bein eloheichem le-emet ve-yatziv lo yafsik. You cannot
interrupt in order to make it as a statement of ה' אלוהיכם
אמת Hashem eloheichem emet that Hashem your God is true, so therefore
even though they are really
different... parts of the דאוונען davening and different sections, but we're trying
to connect them and therefore you cannot interrupt them. אמר רבי אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabi Abba amar Rabi Yochanan, מאי טעמיה דרבי
יהודה? mai ta'ameh d'Rebi Yehuda? What's the reason? דכתיב Dich'tiv because there's
a פסוק pasuk דהשם אלוהיכם אמת. d'Hashem Eloheichem Emet. So we want
to sort of embody that פסוק pasuk in our in this part
of שמע. Shema Now the גמרא Gemara says like this: חוזר ואומר
אמת או אינו חוזר ואומר אמת? Chozer v'omer emet o eino chozer
v'omer emet? So you said השם אלוהיכם אמת, Hashem Eloheichem Emet, right?
And now you have to continue. So after the חזן chazzan gets
up to where he, you know, and he says it, so what
do you do? Do you now say אמת ויציב ונכון וקיים Emet
v'Yatziv v'Nachon v'Kayom or do you just start continuing as ויציב ונכון
וקיים? v'Yatziv v'Nachon v'Kayom? So he said, אמר רבי אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabi Abba amar Rabi Yochanan, חוזר ואומר אמת. chozer v'omer
emet. So first the first opinion of רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan is
you do say אמת emet again now that because then אמת emet
is doing its double duty, it's closing the previous one and then
you put it in its, you know, more natural place אמת ויציב.
emet v'yatziv. רבא אמר, Raba amar, רבא Raba says אינו חוזר ואומר
אמת. eino chozer v'omer emet. No, you don't say it again. You're
connecting it one way, you don't want to sort of, you know,
muddy, you know, that connection by then sort of attaching it more
explicitly to the next section. You have one flow into the other,
and by repeating it, they're not going to flow one into the
other. ההוא דנחית קמיה דרבא, Hahu d'nechis kamei d'Rava, so there's a
certain person that went down in front of רבא. Raba. Again, remember
we said that the person who prays also always has to pray
from a low place. So when we talk about somebody going to
דאוון, daven, they're יורד לפני התיבה, yored lifnei hateiva, they go down
to the ark. And here it's נחית, nachit, again, they go down.
So the person who went to pray, to lead the תפילה, שמעיה
רבא דאמר אמת אמת תרי זימני. sham'ei Rava d'amar emet emet trei
zimnei. He said השם אלוהיכם אמת, Hashem Eloheichem Emet, and then he
said אמת ויציב ונכון וקיים. Emet v'Yatziv v'Nachon v'Kayom. He said אמת
emet twice. So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Raba said, כל
אמת אמת חסיה להאי. kol emet emet chasei l'hai. This guy has
the אמת אמת emet emet sickness. He's, you know, he's on repeat,
אמת אמת emet emet whatever. So he felt that that was inappropriate
to say it twice. Now one wonders because of that language is
maybe that the reason, sort of like why you're not supposed to
say שמע שמע Shema Shema or מודים מודים, Modim Modim, you know,
concerns about maybe reflecting a dualistic nature of God and so on,
that maybe the doubling is itself, you know, a particular problem, particularly
remember that they were dealing with, you know, a sort of Zoroastrian
and dualistic type of a context and they were very sensitive to
these ideas of doubling. So that might be an aspect as well.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב יוסף, amar
Rav Yosef, כמה מעליא האי שמעתתא. kama ma'alya hai shmaita. How beautiful,
how wonderful is the following teaching that I'm about to share with
you. דכי אתא רב שמואל בר יהודה, D'chi ata Rav Shmuel bar
Yehuda, when רב שמואל בר יהודה Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda came from
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר, he said, אמרי במערבא, amri b'ma'rava, here's
what they say in the west, here's what they say in ישראל.
Israel. ערבית: Arvit: דבר בני ישראל ואמרת אליהם אני השם אלוהיכם אמת.
Daber bnei Yisrael v'amarta aleihem Ani Hashem Eloheichem emet. That actually they
have a shorter שמע Shema in מעריב. Maariv. They don't say the
whole פרשת ציצית, Parshat Tzitzit, they say the first half of the
first פסוק pasuk. and then they jump to the last half of
the last פסוק. pasuk They say, right, they say דבר בני ישראל
ואמרת אליהם. Daber bnei Yisrael v'amarta aleihem. So we know the end
of the פסוק pasuk is
ועשו לכם ציצית. v'asu lachem tzitzit. But here it's דבר בני ישראל
ואמרת אליהם, Daber bnei Yisrael v'amarta aleihem, jump to the end:
השם אלוהיכם אמת. Hashem Eloheichem emet. So you sort of have created
a new פסוק pasuk by hybrid, the first half of the first
one and the last half of the last one. So that's what
they do.
Now, no you can't do that. כל פסוק דלא פסקיה משה אנן
לא פסקינן.
Kol pasuk d'lo paskei Moshe anan
lo paskei.
I know, I know. It's a problem. Like I said last time
we learned that, you know, these rules are only as good as
until we violate them. But anyway, but the more important the other
point I want to focus on is why are they fooling around
with the פרשת ציצית Parshat Tzitzit for מעריב? Maariv? So if you
look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi here says,
third line down in רש"י Rashi near the end of the line:
קריאת שמע של ערבית אין קורין בה פרשת ציצית כולה. Kriyat Shema
shel Arvit ein korin ba parshat tzitzit kula. They would not read
the entire פרשת ציצית. Parshat Tzitzit. Why? לפי שאין מצות ציצית בלילה,
Lefi she'ein mitzvat tzitzit balayla, because the מצוה mitzvah of ציצית tzitzit
doesn't apply at night. אבל מתחילין אותו מפסיקים בה ומדלגים בה לאני
השם אלוהיכם אמת. Aval matchilin oto mafsikim ba u'medalgim ba l'Ani Hashem
Eloheichem Emet. So you would jump over the ציצית tzitzit part. You
didn't want to read about the ציצית tzitzit part because that's not
applied at night, so you read the beginning, you read the end.
So רש"י Rashi said it's all about the מצוה mitzvah of ציצית.
tzitzit.
יציאת מצרים. Yetziat Mitzrayim.
But of course, right. Exactly. But of course what the other possibility
here is like we said when we discussed the issue about ציצית
אינה נוהגת בלילה, tzitzit einah noheg balayla, it could mean that ציצית
tzitzit is not בלילה, balayla, it could mean the פרשת ציצית Parshat
Tzitzit in the sense of there's no מצוה mitzvah of יציאת מצרים
בלילות, Yetziat Mitzrayim balailos, which was an opinion. So it could be
that this is reflecting that approach and therefore they say who needs
to say the whole פרשת ציצית? Parshat Tzitzit? We don't need to
do יציאת מצרים בלילות. Yetziat Mitzrayim balailos. So you still want to
keep the structure of the liturgy, so you jump to the end:
השם אלוהיכם אמת, Hashem Eloheichem emet, and that allows you to flow
into that that idea. השם אלוהיכם אמת Hashem Eloheichem emet by the
way is a nice is a nice parallel to שמע ישראל השם
אלוהינו, Shema Yisrael Hashem Eloheinu, allows you to flow into the ברכה.
bracha That's what we're going to do to create but we don't
need to really say this because anyway maybe you're not מזכיר יציאת
מצרים בלילות. mazkir Yetziat Mitzrayim balailos. So that certainly seems to be
a very nice way of understanding this. רש"י Rashi is consistent that
he says it's not about not having a מצוה mitzvah of יציאת
מצרים בלילות, Yetziat Mitzrayim balailos, but it's about the ציצית tzitzit themselves
are not נוהג noheg and therefore they didn't feel need to read
it. Now Michael says very nice. But then when did you יוצא
yotze יציאת מצרים בלילות? yetzias mitzrayim baleilos? So the answer to that
is what we say in the ברכה bracha. that follows ציצית, tzitzis,
because in that ברכה bracha we mention at length יציאת מצרים. yetzias
mitzrayim. So we're יוצא yotze יציאת מצרים yetzias mitzrayim by the ברכה
bracha... even though we're skipping the פרשה parsha of ציצית. tzitzis. That's
the way רש"י Rashi understands. Okay, so let's now continue in the
גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר ליה
אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back to רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef, מאי מעליותא, mai ma'alyusa, what's so beautiful about that? What's
so wonderful about that? ואמר רב כהנא אמר רב, v'amar Rav Kahana
amar Rav, רב כהנא Rav Kahana says in the name of רב,
לא יתחיל, lo yaschil, that you shouldn't start. If you don't want
to say the third פרשה parsha of שמע Shema, at night, don't
start
it. Okay? ואם התחיל יגמור, v'im hitchil yigmor, finish it. If you're
going to start it, finish it. So don't do this like Michael
says, don't do this cutting up of פסוקים psukim and rearranging. If
you want to leave the whole thing out, leave the whole thing
out. But if you're going to start it, then finish. Okay, but
again, notice the theme that you don't have to say the last
פרשה parsha of שמע, Shema the פרשה parsha of ציצית tzitzis at
night. Anyway, so he says, so I don't like what they do
over there in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. סבר וכי תימא savar v'chi
teima ואמרת אליהם v'amarta aleihem לא הוי התחלה, lo havei haschala, maybe
that דבר אל בני ישראל ואמרת אליהם daber el b'nei Yisrael v'amarta
aleihem is not starting it enough that requires you to finish. Maybe
you have to say the whole first פסוק pasuk. to be required
to finish. So maybe it's acceptable. No. דאמר רב שמואל בר יצחק
אמר רב d'amar Rav Shmuel bar Yitzchak amar Rav דבר אל בני
ישראל daber el b'nei Yisrael לא הוי התחלה. lo havei haschala. If
all you said was דבר אל בני ישראל, daber el b'nei Yisrael,
you haven't started it enough, it's not considered starting, and then you
could just leave the whole thing out. ואמרת אליהם הוי התחלה. v'amarta
aleihem havei haschala. But once you get up to ואמרת אליהם, v'amarta
aleihem, now you're really into the פרשה parsha and if you said
that much you have to finish it. So אמר רב פפא amar
Rav Papa קסברי במערבא, kasvari b'ma'arava, here's what they hold in ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. They hold, meaning that you could say they just
hold that you don't have to finish do the whole thing, but
no, here's how he's explaining the debate. קסברי במערבא kasvari b'ma'arava ואמרת
אליהם נמי לא הוי התחלה v'amarta aleihem nami lo havei haschala עד
דאמר ועשו להם ציצית. ad d'amar v'asu lahem tzitzis. Until you get
into the ציצית, tzitzis, you're not into, until you've mentioned ציצית, tzitzis,
you don't have to talk about ציצית. tzitzis. So even if you
get up to ואמרת אליהם, v'amarta aleihem, you can skip to the
end. But once you say ציצית, tzitzis, then you gotta finish talking
about ציצית. tzitzis. Okay, so that, but in principle everyone agrees you
could drop the thing out, the question is how far in do
you have to then finish it. By the way, this does more
support רש"י's Rashi's read, I would have to admit, that the issue
is the ציצית tzitzis part. That once you're saying ציצית, tzitzis, might
as well finish. But otherwise we can skip over ציצית. tzitzis. And
that's what רש"י Rashi says, the issue here is not about יציאת
מצרים yetzias mitzrayim not being נוהג בלילות, noheg baleilos, but about ציצית
tzitzis not being נוהג. noheg. That's the way רש"י Rashi understands. Anyway,
now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Where was I? אמר רב פפא קסברי במערבא ואמרת אליהם נמי לא
הוי התחלה עד דאמרי ועשו להם ציצית. amar Rav Papa kasvari b'ma'arava
v'amarta aleihem nami lo havei haschala ad d'amri v'asu lahem tzitzis. אמר
אביי amar Abaye הלכך, hilchach, therefore, אנן אתחולי מתחלינן, anan as-chulei mas-chalinan,
we, we begin by saying ואמרת אליהם, v'amarta aleihem, you know, דבר
אל בני ישראל ואמרת אליהם. daber el b'nei Yisrael v'amarta aleihem. Why?
דקא מתחלי במערבא, d'ka mas-chalei b'ma'arava, that's what they do in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael that they say up to ואמרת אליהם. v'amarta aleihem.
But וכיון דאתחלינן מגמר נמי גמרינן, v'keivan d'as-chalinan migmar nami gamrinan, but
we don't do like they do where they can then skip to
the end. Once we've gotten that far in, we're going to have
to say the whole thing. דאמר רב כהנא אמר רב d'amar Rav
Kahana amar Rav לא יתחיל ואם התחיל יגמור, lo yaschil v'im hitchil
yigmor, because we say once you get started you have to end.
So basically, since nobody says, what, I will paraphrase this by saying
the following: since in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they don't accept the
idea, I shouldn't say nobody says, in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they
don't accept the idea that you can completely drop it, they require
that you at least start it, we're going to follow them in
that practice that you can't completely drop it. But now that we're
starting it, we're also going to follow the practice that if you
start you have to finish. So we're stuck and we're going to
say it the whole thing. So what you see here is it
sounds like in בבל Bavel they said three פרשיות parshiyos of שמע
Shema at night and in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they did an
abbreviated version of the פרשה parsha of
ציצית. tzitzis. אמר אביי amar Abaye הלכך אנן אתחולי מתחלינן, hilchach anan
as-chulei mas-chalinan, we, I'm sorry, I just read that. Okay. חייא בר
רב אמר, Chiya bar Rav amar, אמר אני ה' אלהיכם צריך לומר
אמת, amar Ani Hashem Elokeichem tzarich lomar emes, לא אמר אני ה'
אלהיכם אינו צריך לומר אמת. lo amar Ani Hashem Elokeichem eino tzarich
lomar emes. If you said the end, we were talking about the
beginning and finishing, but now we're talking about what we talked about
the idea of the connection of אני ה' אלהיכם Ani Hashem Elokeichem
to אמת. emes. So if, maybe some people jumped over the end
of the last פסוק. Or רש"י Rashi says maybe you're not saying
the פרשה parsha of ציצית tzitzis at all, like that was an
option that at least one person was suggesting. So if you're not
saying the פרשה parsha of ציצית tzitzis or if you're not saying
אני ה' אלהיכם, Ani Hashem Elokeichem, you don't say אמת. emes. Now
what does it mean don't say אמת? emes? You don't say the
word אמת, emes, you start with ויציב? v'yatziv? So no, it seems
like you don't say the whole ברכה bracha, of אמת. emes. So
now the גמרא Gemara has got a problem. Let's take a look
at what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says והא
בעי לאדכורי יציאת
מצרים. v'ha ba'ei l'adkurei yetzias mitzrayim.
So here the גמרא is understanding, ah, you gotta do יציאת מצרים
yetzias mitzrayim now. This again is really, you know, רש"י's Rashi's read
that of course you're doing יציאת מצרים yetzias mitzrayim at night, the
whole issue was ציצית. tzitzis. So I understood if you were going
to do a skip over the third פרשה, parsha, at least you're
saying the last ברכה. bracha The last ברכה bracha, has יציאת מצרים.
yetzias mitzrayim. But if you're not going to say the last פרשה
parsha and not the last
ברכה... bracha, So the גמרא says,
so what's the גמרא׳ס Gemara's answer?
ומה v'ma ואמר הכי. v'amar hachi. No, so you don't say the
whole big אמת ויציב ונכון וקיים וישר emes v'yatziv v'nachon v'kayam v'yashar
blah blah blah, that you don't say. But you're still going to
say a ברכה, bracha right? שמע Shema has to have a ברכה
bracha. at the end. So here's what you're going to say: מודים
אנחנו לפניך ה׳ אלהינו שהוצאתנו מארץ מצרים ופדיתנו מבית עבדים ועשית לנו
נסים וגבורות על הים ושרנו לך. modim anachnu lefanecha Hashem elokeinu shehotzeitanu
me'eretz mitzrayim upaditanu mibeis avadim ve'asita lanu nisim ugevuros al hayam v'sharanu
l'cha. So we thank you for doing יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim and
we thanked you and so on. So meaning first of all what
is fascinating about this גמרא is you see
that the liturgy, the structure was still in flux. There were differences
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel and in בבל. Bavel. Even in a
community there was a certain amount of latitude. If you want to
start, then finish. You don't want to start, don't do it. So
there was obviously this period of flux. Number, that's number one interesting.
Number two is this idea that the connection of ה׳ אלהיכם אמת,
Hashem elokeichem emes, where what the גמרא׳ס Gemara's basically saying is, if
for some reason you don't have the ה׳ אלהיכם, Hashem elokeichem, you
don't do the אמת emes part. That's underscoring the statement of אני
ה׳ אלהיכם. ani Hashem elokeichem. You still need a final ברכה, bracha
you're not going to drop the ברכה, bracha and that ברכה bracha
has to talk about יציאת מצרים, Yetzias Mitzrayim, so we'll have a
different נוסח nusach for that ברכה. bracha But the ברכה bracha that
starts with אמת ויציב emes v'yatziv or the אמת ואמונה, emes v'emuna,
which is for tonight, that is when it connects to אני ה׳
אלהיכם. ani Hashem elokeichem. When it doesn't, we'll have a different נוסח
nusach for the ברכה bracha that emphasizes יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. So
that is quite fascinating because it really seems
גאל ישראל, ga'al Yisroel, right?
I'm sorry? Yeah, and then it would end with גאל ישראל, ga'al
Yisroel, exactly.
גאל ישראל. ga'al Yisroel.
Right, correct, and thank you for pointing that out. That that ברכה
is a ברכה of גאל ישראל. ga'al Yisroel. So the end, the
חתימה chasima of the ברכה is going to be the same, and
the text of יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim is really what feeds into
the ברכה of גאל ישראל, ga'al Yisroel, that's not changing. The question
is the first half of it, the אמת ויציב emes v'yatziv or
the אמת ואמונה, emes v'emuna, and that the גמרא׳ס Gemara's saying is
that part is only important if we can connect it to the
אני ה׳ אלהיכם. ani Hashem elokeichem. Now I will just end by
saying that when you put all that together it sounds like the
פשט pshat that's supposed to be understood is, when we say אמת
ויציב ונכון וקיים וישר, emes v'yatziv v'nachon v'kayam v'yashar, it sort of
makes that statement about the אני ה׳ אלהיכם, ani Hashem elokeichem, that
that is אמת ויציב ונכון וקיים וישר. emes v'yatziv v'nachon v'kayam v'yashar.
Right, that seems to be why the גמרא is so insistent on
connecting it and then just dropping it if they're not connected. But
an earlier תוספות doesn't like that. He says, no, no, no, the
אמת ויציב ונכון וקיים וישר emes v'yatziv v'nachon v'kayam v'yashar is the
things we're going to say afterwards, but not about God, because
תוספות says, there's an idea of not heaping on all of these
praises on God because it just
undermines. So we don't go overboard and list fifteen different things that
God is amazing. So תוספות wants to say the אמת ויציב ונכון
emes v'yatziv v'nachon is not about אני ה׳ אלהיכם, ani Hashem elokeichem,
it is about the next part. But this גמרא really seems like
no, it is very connected, it's not considered בין הפרקים, bein haprakim,
and if you're not going to say אני ה׳ אלהיכם, ani Hashem
elokeichem, you're not going to say that. And I'll just end by
saying that given the bottom line is that in בבל Bavel they
were saying the third פרשה parsha of שמע Shema and in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisroel they
weren't, they were doing a very abbreviated version. And it's clear that
the בבלי Bavli here at the end says you have to do
יציאת מצרים בלילות. Yetzias Mitzrayim baleilos. But again
it still leaves open the question of whether in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisroel how fully accepted was it that you do יציאת מצרים בלילות.
Yetzias Mitzrayim baleilos. Maybe that is part of the reason they did
not do the third פרשה parsha of שמע in addition to what
רש״י Rashi says about just the ציצית tzitzis not being applicable at
night. Okay, so we will pick up here
tomorrow.
לילה טוב laila tov everyone.